Caspar Wistar Papers 1794-1893 1794-1817 Mss.B.W76
American Philosophical Society
Caspar Wistar Papers
1794-1817
Mss.B.W76
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Volume(s) 44 items
This is primarily a collection of letters and manuscripts sent to Wistar by prominent men who were among his many correspondents. These documents reflect his broad interests, including botany, paleontology, medicine, the American Philosophical Society, and André Michaux's plans for exploring the Missouri.
Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
Bibliography
Rubincam, Milton, "The Wistar-Wister Family: A Pennsylvania Family's Contributions Toward American Cultural Development, Pennsylvania History, Vol.20, no.2, 1953.
Early American History Note
This bound volume contains approximately forty-four content rich letters written to Caspar Wistar, a prominent Philadelphian and scientist. Wistar’s wide-ranging scientific interests are captured in the broad content of these letters. Topics of discussion include APS business, distillation, fossils and skeletons, scientific expeditions, and various letters of introductions sent to Wistar. A significant number are written in French.
Related Archival Materials note
Wistar, Caspar, Medical Commonplace book, 1796-1813. 1 vol. (Call no.: 616.928 W765)
Wistar, Caspar, Notes of Anatomical lectures, ca. 1781-1809. 3 vols. (Call no.: 610.4 W76)
Corrêa da Serra, José Francesco. Note necrologique sur le Docteur Wistar, 1818. 1 vol. (Call no.: B W76c)
Biographical tributes to Caspar Wistar, 1818 (Call no.: B W76a)
Other manuscripts collections containing items by or relating to Caspar Wistar can be found at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, the Rare Books and Manuscripts Department of the University of Pennsylvania Library, and the Library of Congress.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Mrs. Esther F. Wistar in memory of her husband, Dr. Mifflin Wistar, 1893.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection is available on microfilm (Film 1254).
Scope and Contents note
The Wistar Papers consist primarily of letters sent to Caspar Wistar by prominent scientific colleagues. These reflect his broad interests, including botany, paleontology, medicine, the American Philosophical Society, and André Michaux's plans for exploring the Missouri. The correspondents include Samuel Brown, Adrien Gilles Camper, J. F. Corrêa da Serra, Georges L. C. F. D. Cuvier, John Eliot, John G. E. Heckewelder, Thomas Jefferson, François André Michaux, Samuel L. Mitchill, Ambroise M. F. J., Baron de Palisot de Beauvois, Alire Raffeneau-Delile, Wilhelm Gottlieb Tilesius von Tilenau, David Bailie Warden, and Hugh Williamson. These materials were selected by Esther F. Wistar and presented to the APS in 1893 in honor of her late husband, Dr. Mifflin Wistar, Caspar Wistar's son.
The letters are presented in a bound volume. They have been microfilmed (Film #1254).
Biographical/Historical note
Caspar Wistar (1761-1818, APS 1787) was a Philadelphia physician and paleontologist. He was a professor at the University of Pennsylvania for three decades, and he served the American Philosophical Society in various offices, including that of president. He was the host of the popular weekly gatherings of local and visiting learned men that became known as the Wistar Parties.
He was born in Philadelphia, the son of Richard Wistar (1727-1781), a glass manufacturer, and Sarah Wyatt Wistar (1733-1771). His seven siblings included his younger sister Catharine, who was married to Benjamin Franklin’s grandson William Bache. Wistar is sometimes called Caspar Wistar, Jr., to distinguish him from his grandfather, also named Caspar Wistar (1696-1752). The elder Caspar was a merchant and glassmaker who had moved from Wald-Hilspach, Germany, to Philadelphia in 1717.
Born a Quaker, Wistar was educated at the Friends School at Fourth and Walnut Streets in Philadelphia. At age sixteen he volunteered as a nurse at the Battle of Germantown in 1777. It is said that this experience inspired him to become a physician. He commenced his medical studies that year, under the physician John Redman and later also with John Jones, a New York physician who had fled to Philadelphia. In 1779 Wistar enrolled in the medical department of what was then called the University of the State of Pennsylvania. In 1782, after receipt of his Bachelor of Medicine, he set out for a three year tour of study in England and Scotland. (Wistar was a practicing Friend throughout his life; however, prior to his departure he had trouble securing a certificate that testified to his diligent adherence to conduct becoming to a Friend for he had fallen “into Scandalous & alarming temptation of being engaged in a duel.”) While still a student he was elected one of the presidents of the Royal Medical Society and also president of the Society for the Further Investigation of Natural History. During his stay in England and Scotland he made the acquaintance of several notable figures, including James Boswell, Sir James McIntosh and William Cullen (1710-1790, APS 1768). In 1786 he graduated from the University of Edinburgh with a Doctorate of Medicine.
Back in Philadelphia, Wistar established a private medical practice that soon grew into one of the largest in the city. He was also elected to the College of Physicians and served as a physician to the Philadelphia Dispensary. In 1788 he became a professor of chemistry at the medical school of the College of Philadelphia in 1788. After the merger of the College with the University of the State of Pennsylvania in 1791, Wistar became an adjunct professor of anatomy, midwifery and surgery. In 1793 he joined the staff of the Pennsylvania Hospital. He nearly lost his life during the yellow fever epidemic of 1793 after being stricken by the disease while assisting his friend Benjamin Rush (1745-1813, APS 1768) in fighting the epidemic. Differences of opinion regarding treatment of this disease, including the drastic use of bleeding and purging, eventually caused a breech in their friendship. Nevertheless, Wistar remained Rush’s colleague at the Pennsylvania Hospital until 1810. In 1808 he was appointed to the chair in anatomy which had formerly been occupied by William Shippen. Wistar remained on the Penn faculty until his death in 1818.
Wistar was a popular teacher who enlivened his presentations with drawings and models that made it easier for students to follow his lectures and demonstrations. He developed a number of unique teaching aids, some of which were life-sized anatomical models made of dried and wax-injected human limbs and organs. Others were fashioned of wood, carved by America's first professional sculptor, William Rush. Two years before his death, Wistar appointed Dr. William Edmonds Horner (1793-1853, APS 1819), his long-time assistant in anatomy, as caretaker of these valuable models. Horner later enlarged the collection and opened the first anatomical museum in the United States, the Wistar and Horner Museum. The collection eventually passed to the Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology, the first independent medical research facility established in the United States. The Institute, which was founded in 1892 by Wistar's great-nephew, Isaac J. Wistar (1827-1905, APS 1893), was named in honor of Caspar Wistar.
Wistar's reputation drew medical students to Philadelphia from around the world. His anatomy courses became so large that they eventually had to be divided into sections. Wistar wrote the first and very successful treatise on anatomy published in the United States, titled A System of Anatomy (2 vols., 1811, 1814). However, he was widely respected not only for his medical knowledge, but also for his general breadth of knowledge, which included the humanities as well as the sciences. In fact, while Wistar made few contributions to medical literature – his only medical article, a description of the sphenoid sinuses, was published the year he died –, he contributed several papers on scientific subjects outside of medicine, including paleontology and botany. His reputation as an authority on fossil bones was established as early as 1787, when he and Timothy Matlack (1730-1823, APS 1780) presented a paper on what may have been the first dinosaur bone examined by American scientists. In 1799 he published an article on the bones of the giant “megalonix” that Thomas Jefferson had deposited with the American Philosophical Society two years earlier. The essay, which appeared in the Society’s Transactions, is regarded as the first technical study of professional quality to be published by an American or in America in the field of vertebrate paleontology. One historian has called the achievement “almost incredible in view of the paleontological naïveté of his associates and of the lack of comparative materials.” Wistar also collaborated in Jefferson’s efforts to obtain the bones of the mastodon and associated animals, and he studied specimens returned from the Lewis and Clark Expedition. Some of his observations on the latter were published posthumously in the Transactions.
Wistar was as popular with his professional colleagues as he was with Philadelphia’s literati. He was particularly known for his hospitality, and his home was the weekly meeting place of students and scientists, including locals and distinguished foreign visitors. The physician Charles Caldwell (1772-1853, APS 1796) recalled later that “The company met, without ceremony, on a stated evening, where in the midst of a succession of suitable refreshments, the time passed away, oftentimes until a late hour, in agreeable, varied, and instructive discourse.” The “company” included, for example, Alexander von Humboldt (1769-1859, APS 1804), who was a guest of honor when he visited Philadelphia in 1800, as well as the French botanist François Andre Michaux (1749-1802). A frequent attendant after his arrival in the United States in 1812 was the Abbé Corrêa da Serra (1750–1823, APS 1812), the Portuguese diplomat and naturalist. Wistar, who shared with the Abbé a serous interest in botany, became his close friend and accompanied him on several expeditions. The Wistar Parties were so popular that several leading members of the American Philosophical Society, including Stephen DuPonceau (1760-1844, APS 1791), continued to host them regularly after Wistar’s death.
Wistar was active in numerous scientific and learned organizations. He was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1787. He served as its curator in 1793 and vice-president in 1795, before succeeding Thomas Jefferson as president in 1815, a position he held until his death. Wistar was especially supportive of the Historical and Literary Committee that was established in 1815 to serve as the collection, research, and publishing arm of the Society. He was elected a Fellow of the College of Physicians in 1788, and he served as a trustee of the College of Philadelphia from 1789 to 1791. In 1815 he was elected an honorary member of the Literary and Philosophical Society of New York. The botanist Thomas Nuttall (1786-1859, APS 1817) honored Wistar by naming the plant genus Wisteria after him.
Wistar’s support of many progressive causes is reflected in his affiliation with a number of reform organizations. He was a founder of the Society for Circulating the Benefit of Vaccination, and he belonged to the Pennsylvania Prison Society, the Humane Society, and the Society for the Abolition of Slavery, of which he became president in 1813. In 1791 Wistar bought and then freed a slave “to extricate him from that degraded Situation.”
Caspar Wistar died in 1818 after a period of declining health. He was married twice, first in 1788 to Isabella Marshall, who died childless two years later. In 1798 he married Elizabeth Mifflin, with whom he had three children: Dr. Richard Mifflin Wistar, Dr. Mifflin Wistar, and Elizabeth Wistar. There were no grandchildren.
Ambroise M. F. J., Baron de Palisot de Beauvois; Brown, Samuel, 1769-1830; Camper, Adrien Gilles, 1759-1820; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823; Cuvier, Georges, Baron, 1769-1832; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855; Mitchill, Samuel L., (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831; Raffeneau-Delile, Alire, 1778-1850; Tilesius von Tilenau, Wilhelm Gottlieb; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845; American Philosophical Society; Botany; General Correspondence; International Travel; Medicine; Medicine--19th century; Natural History; Paleontology--19th century; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Travel; Yellow fever
- Letters to Caspar Wistar, 1794-1893; 1.0 vol. (Volume 1)
  - Letter to the president of the American philosophical society, Sept., 1893; 13x8; Wistar, Esther Fisher Smith, b. 1818
    Scope and Contents note
    Typed L.S. 1p.and end. (see Letters to C. Wistar, p.ii.) Gives C.Wistar's letters as memorial to her husband, Dr. Mifflin Wistar.
  - Letter to [Caspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, July 19, 1794; 9x6-1/4; Sylvestre
    Geneva, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.1) Desires to come to America and settle in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to [Caspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, May 20, 1796; 9x7-1/2; Palisot de Beauvois, Ambrose-Marie-François-Joseph, 1752-1820
    Charleston, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 2.) Friendly letter. Concerning natural history. Refers to the APS.
  - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, April 25, 1798; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Palisot de Beauvois, Ambrose-Marie-François-Joseph, 1752-1820
    Richmond, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.3.) Concerning the discovery of fossils in Virginia. Refers to the APS. Film 199 Frame 112.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson., May 13, 1797; 4.; McCorckle, Samuel; Spring, Samuel
    General note
    not located 4/2010
    L.S., 1. p. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.4.) Concerning the ruins of a wall of great antiquity in North Carolina.
    Freeman Guide 1233.
  - Letter to Caspar Wistar, Philadelphia, Feb. 14, 1797; 12-3/4x8; Mitchill, Samuel L., (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 5.) Refers to Jefferson. Concerning the distillation of fresh water from salt water.
  - Letter to Jonathan Williams, Philadelphia, June 30, 1798; 10x8; Mitchill, Samuel L., (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831
    New York, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar no. 6.) Friendly letter. Concerning the APS, fossils, C.W.Peale, and minerology of New York. Freeman Guide 1749.
  - Letter to Caspar Wistar, Philadelphia, Oct. 12, 1799; 9x7-1/4; Massachusetts Historical Society
    Boston, A.L.S.: John Eliot. 2p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar,no. 7.) Notifies him of his election to membership. Purposes of the society.
  - Extrait d'un Ouvrage... de Quadrupedes., [Nov. 17, 1800]; 8.; Cuvier, Georges, Baron, 1769-1832
    (see Letters to C. Wistar, no. 8.) Printed prospectus of a work of G. Cuvier on Quadrupeds received by the American Philosophical Society, 3 April 1801.
  - Letter to [Thomas] Jefferson, Aug. 24, 1806; 10x8; Brown, Samuel, 1769-1830
    A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 9.) Concerning fossil bones. Refers to Wistar and the APS. Film 199 Frame 445
  - Newspaper clipping., 9a.
  - Letter to [Caspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Nov. 15, 1807; 10x7-3/4; Raffeneau-Delile, Alire, 1778-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 4p.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.10.) Concerning medicine, especially William Hunter's experiments. Refers to Patterson
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Nov. 24, 1808; 9-3/4x8-1/2; Raffeneau-Delile, Alire, 1778-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.11.) Friendly letter. Refers to Michaux, Humboldt and Hosack.
  - Concerning the black vomit [yellow fever], Nov. 15, 1809; 10x7-1/2; Raffeneau-Delile, Alire, 1778-1850
    Paris, D.S. 5p.and end. Sent to C.Wistar. Philadelphia. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.12.)
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Sept. 24, 1810; 9x7; Raffeneau-Delile, Alire, 1778-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.14.) Friendly letter. Concerning Michaux, Warden, Jefferson and Madison. Film 199 Frame 682
  - Extract of minutes to the American philosophical society, Oct. 10, 1808; 13x8-1/2; Académie des sciences (France)
    Film 199 Frame 221
    Paris, D.S.: Cuvier. 4p. In French. (see Letters to C. Wistar, no.15.) Concerning Jefferson's gift of fossils to the society.
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Oct. 21, 1809; 8-1/4x6-1/4; Raffeneau-Delile, Alire, 1778-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.13.) Medical news. Refers to Humboldt and Michaux.
  - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, Nov. 14, 1808; 13-1/4x8-1/2; Académie des sciences (France)
    Paris, L.S.: Tenon and G.Cuvier. 1p.and end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 16.) Thanks for the fossils.
  - Letter to J[o]hn Vaughan, Philadelphia, May 27, 1809; 9-1/2x7-1/4; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p.and add., In French (see Letter to C.Wistar, no. 17.) Concerning anatomy. Refers to Cuvier and the APS.
  - Letter to Casp[a]r Wistar, Philadelphia, Nov. 29, 1809; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 18.) Friendly Letter. Refers to Patterson, Correa de Serra and the APS.
  - Letter to C[aspar], Wistar, Philadelphia, Sept. 7, 1810; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 19.) Friendly Letter. Refers to Correa de Serra.
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Dec. 5, 1811; 9x7-1/4; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p.and add. In French. (see Letters to Caspar Wistar, no. 20.) Concerning medical publications. Refers to J.Vaughan and Correa de Serra.
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Jan. 28, 1812; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 4p.,add. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar,no.21) Friendly letter. Concerning medical publications. Refers to Patterson, J. Vaughan and Lewis and Clark's expedition.
  - Letter to C[aspar Wistar, Philadelphia, June 26, 1814; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p. and add.end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 22.) Concerning publications on medicine.
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Sept. 17, 1816; 9-1/2x7-1/4; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S.with initials. 3p.and add. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.23.) Forwards publication. Refers to Delile and Correa de Serra.
  - Letter to C[aspar], Wistar, Philadelphia, Dec. 18, 1817; 9-3/4x7-1/4; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p.and add. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar,no.24.) Business. Concerning medical books.
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wister, Philadelphia, March 17; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    [received] A.L.S. 2p. and add.,end.by J.Vaughan. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 25.) Forwards Publications. [to the society].
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, undated; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. In French. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 26.) Friendly letter. Refers to Correa de Serra, J. Vaughan and the APS.
  - Directions to André Michaux for exploring the west, April 30, 1793; 9-1/4x7-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    Freeman Guide 2963. Film 199 Frame 106
    D.in hand of Jefferson. 4p.,end. (see Letters to Wistar, no. 27.) Cf. Minutes, pp.215-216.
  - Letter to [Caspar Wistar or Thomas Jefferson], July 31, 1809; 9-3/4x8-1/4; Camper, Adrian Gilles, 1759-1820
    Francker, A.L.S. 4p. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 28.) Concerning fossils. Concerning Publications sent to APS. Refers to Michaux and his membership in the APS, Cuvier, and Palisot de Beauvois. FILM 199 FRAME 681
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Nov. 10, 1809; 8-3/4x7-1/2; Camper, Adrian Gilles, 1759-1820
    Francker, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 29.) Sent publications to the APS with a letter to Jefferson. Asks for another certificate of membership. Refers to Michaux. FILM 199 FRAME 680
  - Letter to [Caspar Wistar], June 2, 1815; 12-1/2x7-3/4; Camper, Adrian Gilles, 1759-1820
    Francker, A.L.S. 4p. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 30.) Friendly letter. Concerning fossils, natural history, Rembrandt Peale and the mastodon. Refers to J. Vaughan, Michaux, B.S.Barton and Humboldt.
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, June 20, 1816; 9-3/4x8-1/4; Camper, Adrian Gilles, 1759-1820
    Francker, A.L.S. 4p. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 31.) Concerning skeletons, salamaders, the publication of Lewis & Clark journals, and fossils. Refers to the APS, Barton, Cuvier, Humboldt and Maclure.
  - Letter to [Caspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Dec. 4, 1811; 9x7-1/4; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Delivered by Correa de Serra. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 32.) Introduces Correa de Serra and recommends him as a member of the APS.
  - Letter to Gaspard Whistar [Sic], Philadelphia, Sept. 27, 1813; 10x8; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 33.) Friendly letter. Refers to J.Vaughan. Printed: Trans., n.s.,45,127. Davis, "Abbé Correa..."
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Aug. 20, 1814; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Lexington, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 34.) Friendly letter. Will visit Jefferson Refers to Walsh. Printed: APS Tans.,n.s.45,129-130 Davis:"Abbé Correa..." FILM 199 FRAME 679
  - Letter to Casparo Wistar, Oct., 1813; 8-1/4x6-1/2; Tilesius von T., W. G. (Wilhelm Gottlieb Tilesius von Tilenau), 1769-1857
    St. Petersburg, L. 4p.,end. In Latin. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 35.) Concerning skeletons.
  - Letter to C[aspar] Wistar, Philadelphia, Oct., 1813; 9x7; Tilesius von T., W. G. (Wilhelm Gottlieb Tilesius von Tilenau), 1769-1857
    St. Petersburg, L. 14p. (see Letters to Caspar Wistar, no. 36.) Concerning natural history, skeletons, and the Siberian mammoths. Refers to J.Q.Adams and B.S.Barton. Freeman Guide 1518.
  - Letter to [Caspar] Wistar, Jan. 27, 1814; 10x8; Tilesius von T., W. G. (Wilhelm Gottlieb Tilesius von Tilenau), 1769-1857
    St. Petersburg, A.L.S. 4p. In German. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 37.) Thrilled to hear that Wistar is German. Is sending skulls and other bones. Refers to a manuscript of his. Refers to B. Smith Barton.
  - Letter to Caspar Wistar, Philadelphia, May 1, 1815; 8x6; Literary and Philosophical Society of New-York (New York, N.Y.)
    New York, L.S.: Hu[gh] Williamson and Sam[ue]l L. Mitchill. 1p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.38.) Has made him an honorary member.
  - Letter to Caspar Wistar, Philadelphia, June 2, 1816; 10x7-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 39.) Concerning documents pertaining to Indians in Pennsylvania in a publication of the Historical and literary committee. Refers to DuPonceau. Freeman Guide 888.
  - Letter to Caspar Wistar, Philadelphia, July 4, 1816; 10x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no. 40.) Concerning Indians of Pennsylvania. Refers to DuPonceau and the APS. Freeman Guide 888.
  - Letter to Caspar Wistar, Philadelphia, April 26, 1817; 10x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Letters to C.Wistar, no.41.) Has been ill. Refers to DuPonceau.